Year: 1991
79097꼬
It was December 12, 1980
1980년 12월 12일이었어
My partner and I were patrolling Hano Road
난 선배 한 명과 순찰을 돌던 중에
Shit was going down at New World Centre
폭력사건이 발생했다는 소식을 듣고
We rushed over
급이 달려갔지
A gang fight was taking place
현장에선 수십 명이 싸움을 아고 있었고
About fifteen or so were already down
십 수 명은 이미 쓰러져 있었어
Lots of blood on the ground
바닥은 피투성이였고...
Plus a severed hand, still holding a knife
칼을 부여잡은 채 잘린 손도 보였지
My partner told me to draw my piece
선배가 총을 뽑으라는데
I was a rookie so ! did what he told
신참인 난 그 말을 듣고서야 움직였어
But before I could open the holster
내가 종을 막 꺼내려는 순간
My partner already dropped
선배는 이미 내 앞에 쓰러진 우였지
This kid stabbed a pipe into his belly
한 놈이 쇠파이프로 선배 배를 쑤시자
Blood gushed out of the sawed-off opening
피가 쇠파이프를 타고 쏟아 내리더군
I didn't know what to think
순간 아무 생각 없이
I simply put all six of my bullets
그저 6발의 총알을
straight into that kid!
놈을 향해 몽땅 싸버린 거야
I don't remember how many years he got
놈이 몇 년 형을 받았는지 모르지만
But when I saw him again two years ago
2년 전에 그 놈을 만났어
he was boozing in a club, looking sharp
멀짜게 차려 입고 술을 마시는데
His buddies were all Kwun's goons!
상대는 바로 예곤의 부하였어
Evil prevails. Only the good die young
살인, 방화에다가 완전범죄를 하지
I can barely recall my partner's face now
지금은 그 선배 모습이 으릿아지만
l regret
너무 후회 돼
The six bullets weren't put into that kid's skull
6발을 그 놈의 머리에 싸야 아는데
The world shouldn't be like this
세상이 이래서는 안 되지
It's not the way to be, Sam
그건 올바른 길이 아니야, 침!
How long have you been around Tsim Sha Tsui?
침사추이에 얼마나 있었지?
Almost two years now
2년이 다 돼가지
Do you know why I haven't messed with you?
2년 동안 자넬 왜 안 잡은지 알아?
‘Cause I am handsome!
잘 생겼으니까!
Maybe so
그럴 수도 있지
‘Cause I think you're a decent guy
아직 사람으로 보이기 때문이야
I'd rather you be in charge
침사추이가 자네 구역이었다면 내가 편했을 텐데...
Forget about it
됐어!
You couldn't waste the kid even with six bullets
총알 6발로 녀석을 죽이지 않았다면
That makes you a decent guy, too. Right?
자년 좋은 사람이야
I don't want to be one
좋은 사람이 되고 싶진 않아
Kwun gave me everything, even my life
내 목숨은 곤형이 준 거야
If! turned against him
자네 때문에 보스를 배신아면 말이 돼?
I'd be despicable even in your eyes. Right?
아마 자네마저도 날 무시할 걸?
I knew you'd say that
그렇게 나올 줄 알았어
Chivalry means little to the Ngai Family
예가에서 하는 일은 의리가 아니야
The Master often says
형님께서 그러셨지
Retribution knows its time
뿌린 대로 거두는 법이라고
Who knows how you and I will end up?
자네랑 식사를 같이 못할까봐 걱정 돼
Time to work!
일하자!
This early?
벌써? 왜 그렇게 서둘러?
I've got to eat! So do my boys!
다 먹었어 우리 애들도 먹어아지
Take the whole box
가져 가!
That's okay. Keep it
됐어, 여기 둘게
Don't worry about it! Just go!
지우지 말고 그냥 가!
Want to use the back door?
뒷문으로 나가도 돼
Ain't no rules against schmoozing with cops
경찰친구가 있을 수도 있는 거잖아?
The front door's fine. Got used to it
정문으로 갈래! 그게 편해
Prat Avenue!
프랫가!
Is Uncle Kwun in?
곤숙부 계세요?
Uncle Kwun! Someone's looking for you!
곤숙, 손님 오셨어요
Bye, Mary
안녕하세요 메리 누님!
They say this American antique's got...
이건 미제 꼴동품이야
..sweet high, crisp middle and strong bass
고음은 부드럽고 저음은 강력하다지
Bullshit!
웃기는 소리야
180 grand!
18만 달러나 하는데
Who can afford it in Hong Kong?
몇 명이나 사겠어?
Sit
앉아!
Only around ten thousand people can afford it
살 수 있는 사람은 만 명도 안 돼
Sam asked you to be a mole in the force
침형이 너한테 경찰 스파이가 되라는데
If you don't like it, [ can talk to him
네가 원지 않으면 빼내 줄 수 있어
You're my boy after all
년 내 사람이나 마찬가지니까
It's fine with me
괜찮아요
Sure?
정말 괜찮아?
Positive
정말이요
Hand me that bag
그 백 좀 줘봐
Mary
여기요
[ thought you'd been dreading it
기운 없어 보이길래 싫다고 할 줄 알았어
Hide in Tuen Mun till things quiet down
상황이 안 좋으니까 투엔먼에 숨어 있어
Stay fit for the Academy's new term
경찰학교가 개학할 때까지 말이야
The money ! gave you, spend wisely
돈을 좀 줄 테니까 아껴서 쓰고
You like the song?
이 노래 맘에 들어?
Yeah
네!
It's yours
너 줄게
It won't sound as good on another player
다른 오디오에서는 소리가 안 좋아
Someday I'll pick out a good one for you
나중에 돈 좀 벌면 좋은 걸로 사 줄게
What? Don't like it?
왜? 싫어?
Not at all
아니요
Sam gave you this watch, didn't he?
그 시계 침형이 준 건가요?
None of your business
상관 마!
Only you and I...
오늘 밤 일은...
..know about tonight
우리 둘만 아는 거야
I don't want Sam to know
남편에게 알리기 싫어
Why's that?
왜죠?
Women are simple
여자는 단순애
A man treats me well, I'd do anything
사랑에 빠지면 뭐든지 할 수 있지
Now go home. I'm very busy tonight
그만 돌아가 봐 오늘 좀 바빠
It's either you or me
차는 멀쩌잖아 다친 건 나라고!
The boss said I would see blood today
형님이 오늘 피 볼 거라고 그러더니...
Got a Mercedes today, Keung?
벤츠 있어?
l said, "Of course." And here I am!
당연이 있다고 그랬지 결국 이끌 났지만
Otherwise, I wouldn't be here with you
안 그랬음 너 같은 놈 만나지도 않았을 텐데
Mainland girls in arms
예전엔 이 몸도 잘나갔었는데
I don't smoke
담배 안 펴
Let's forget about it. My car's fine
이제 그만해요 차도 멀쩌니까...
See! She says it's all good
거봐, 괜찮다잖아
Dressed all dandy
말끔하게 차려 입고
Don't want any trouble, do you?
사고치고 싶진 않지 안 그래?
Look at me. All beaten up by you
내 끌은 이게 뭐야 얻어터지기나 아고...
Who do you think the judge would believe?
법정에 가면 누굴 믿겠어?
bet you guys never go to Tsim Sha Tsui East, huh?
앞으론 침사추이쪽엔 얼씬도 안 하는 게 좋을걸
Know who I am? I'm Keung!
내가 누군지 알아? 사강이라구
Sam's top dog. Del Piero's boy
한침 형님의 오른팔!
I'll kick your ass every time I see you
너 앞으로 각오애
And you can count on that
알았어?!
How about calling an ambulance, sir?
경찰나리 구급차 좀 불러줍쇼
Look at all the blood!
봐요, 피 으르는 거
Have them bring 500 cc Type O. It's rare!
(형 피로 구애줘요 구하기 힘들거든요
Shut up!
닥치고
Wait till we're back to the station
나랑 경찰서 가서 얘기아자구
l only stole a piece of junk, sir!
차도 멀짜잖아요
What've I done to deserve the OCTB?
움직이지 마
Just shut up!
이봐요!
Does that deserve an OCTB beating?
년 아직
Don't you know you're just a cadet?
경찰학교 학생일 뿐이야
And you are expected to get a medal this year
전교 1등이라도 소용없어
Don't ever let Yip know about this!
이 일은 비밀로 애
What's there to be happy about?
축하는 무슨...
Ten years in the Academy. A rustic hell
경찰학교에서 벌써 10년째인데 이룬 것도 없고
You even managed to get me out
저도 졸업시키셨잖아요
Your case's now ancient history
이제 슬슬 현장으로
Get yourself out
오시는 건 어때요
So what if the Commissioner's Chinese now?
지금도 중국인이 맡고 있긴 하지만
Still six more years till the hand-over
양놈들 옷 벗으려면 6년을 더 기다려야 돼
I'll be 48 by then!
그러면 48살이야
Might as well train a few good cops here!
경찰학교에서 좋은 학생들이나 길려내는 게 낮지
The world is yours after 1997!
1997년 후로야 너네들 세상이지
27149! Cheers!
27149, 건배하자
Been beeping the whole day
하루 종일 삐삐가 울리누만
How come you don't call back?
연락 안 했어?
Girlfriend?
여자친구인가봐?
Cheers, sir! Cheers!
- 드시죠, 건배 - 건배
Just leave me alone!
꺼져
It's none of my business ! don't want to know a thing
난 상관 안 해 알고 싶지 않다구!
Go! Leave me alone!
꺼져! 당장 꺼지란 말아!
Law
이봐, 로!
What do you want?
뭐 하는 거아?
My father just passed way
아버지가 돌아가셨다
It was his wish to inform his children...
아버진 평소 당신께 무슨 일이 생기면
when something bad happened to him!
모든 자식들한테 알리라고 하셨어
Sorry to have bothered you!
귀찮게 해서 미안아다
Stop watching TV! Eat first, Negro!
흑귀, 1 그만 보고 밥이나 먹어
l wonder what they have on Kwun's death
곤숙 사망 소식이 나오나 애서 그러지
Did you do it, Ching?
문증, 니가 그랬어?
I've got a big mouth. Had ! done it...
난 입이 가벼워서
.. you would've heard about it!
내가 했으면 벌써 소문났지
Ask Wah and Gandhi
국화아고 감지한테 물어 봐!
Everybody knows!
다들 알잖아?
But I bet his kids think I did it
그 집 자식들은 내가 그런 줄 알걸?
[ain't scared of nothing
난 검나지 않아
The eldest son's a doctor The youngest a brat
큰 아들은 의사고 막내는 백수잖아
The daughter's married for ages
딸은 시집갔고!
Only the middle son's running the show
둘째 아들이 남아서 일 봐주고 있잖아
If they go too far, I'll show them!
까불기라도 하면 가만 안 둘 거야!
We failed to protect Kwun. It's our fault!
회장님을 보오 못한 건 저희 책임입니다
That's enough, Uncle John
삼숙! 됐어요
Dad used to say
아버지가 그러셨죠
What goes around comes around
뿌린 만큼 거둔다고 말이에요
It came later than expected already
지금까지 무사했던 것만도 다행이에요
Wah, Ching, Negro and Gandhi
국화와 문증 그리고 흑귀, 감지 네 명이
Guess what those four are thinking?
무슨 생각을 하고 있을지 궁금하군
Thank you. Thank you all!
감사합니다, 그럼!
How's mom doing, sis?
누나 어머니는 괜찮으세요?
She's fine. Been sleeping
괜찮아 일찍 잠이 드셨다
Bring some cigs to the morgue for dad
영정 앞에 담배 좀 사다 놓으라셨어
I'll go get them
사 올게요
B Team, watch Tak Shing Street
8팀은 「탁싱'가의 입구를 책임지고
C Team, watch the Austin Road exit...
(팀은 「오스틴'가에 있는
..Of that financial building
『「파이낸셜'빌딩 입구를 지킨다
It has two exits
이 건물은 출입구가 두 개다
One on Tak Shing Street. One on Austin...
아나는 「탁싱'가 하나는 「오스틴'
Sorry
미안!
Hello?
여보세요?
Something this big, why didn't you call?
그렇게 중대한 일을 왜 말하지 않았나?
l called everybody the minute it happened!
일이 터지자마자 알린 거야
Kwun's boys can't sit still for sure
예곤이 죽었으니 시끄럽겠군
Shit will hit the fan tonight!
오늘 침사추이에서 일이 터질 거야
It's the 14th already. You know that?
오늘이 14일이잖아
The 14th. Time to pay the Ngai Family
14일이면 예가에 세금을 내는 날이야
So let me be the jackass
껄끄러운 말을 먼저 하지
I'm not paying the Ngai's any more
이번 달부터는 세금 안 낼 거야
What do you three think?
형들 생각은 어때?
Inspector Wong
황 국장!
What's up?
- 침! - 왜?
What're your men doing outside Wah's building?
국화네 빌딩 밑에서 들 하는 건가?
Not a good day for chit chat
나중에 얘기해
Are you into something?
뭐 하는 건데?
Fine, fine. Next time
됐어 나중에 통화애!
What's the occasion?
많이 모였네?
Come on. Where's my seat?
나도 좀 앉자고!
Only if you're here for the food
침형이 오면 기분이 좋다니까
All other businesses have to wait
일 얘기는 다음에 해아겠어
The food. It's all about the food
먹어! 먹자구!
Tonight's gonna be the shit!
오늘 밤은 쉽지 않겠는데?
Let the Big Four do their things
소두목 네 명이 하는 대로 나뒷다가
We'll deal with the aftermath
수습만 하면 돼
Don't let them start fighting
싸움이 나게 하면 안돼
Or you'll see bodies
싸움이 나면 사상자가 생길 거야
What? Not satisfied?
그래서, 불만인가?
You know the rule. Pick a card
여기서 한 장만 골라 봐!
Okay. Higher points win
높은 숫자가 이기는 거야
Come on!
자!
There's nothing left to talk about
지금 바쁘다 그래, 날 왜 찾는데?
What's up, Hau?
안녕하시오? 예 회장!
Wah
국화!
Nothing much
그냥 그렇소
Heard you're planning a casino in Macau
요즘 마카오에 가서 사업을 한다면서?
I've got the government in my pocket
정부쪽엔 얘기애 뒷으니까
How about a joint venture?
나하고 같이 애보는 게 어때?
Uncle Kwun's dead
곤숙은 죽었어
I'm not in the mood
난 그런 데 흥미 없어
lsee
좋아
The Macau trip wasn't all business
마카오에 간 이유가 사업 때문만 아니라
I know you had fun with Gandhi's wife
감지 마누라아고 즐기러 간 거 알아
Sorry, but I can't let go of my casino in Macau
미안해, 마카오사업을 포기할 수 없어
Gotta go
먼저 갈게
What are Sam's people doing?
한침 쪽 애들은 뭐하고 있어?
I know Wah paid up
국화가 세금을 낸 건 이미 알아
Don't change the subject
엇소리 말고
Tell me something I don't know!
내가 모르는 것만 얘기해, 알았어?
Call me when you get your shit straight!
똑바로 알고 다시 전화애
Hau took care of Wah in ten minutes
예 회장이 10분도 안 돼서 국화를 설득시킨 걸로 봐서
The Big Four are having a tough time
오늘 밤엔 네 두목이 아무 짓 못할걸!
Hau took out a million's worth of coke
예 회장이 백만 달러어지 마약을 가져왔대
What?
뭐야?
Mafia road block or what?
소폭들이 길을 막아?
[ don't know why Wah paid up, Hau
예 회장, 국화가 왜 냈는지 모르겠지만
But I ain't gonna negotiate
었든 협상할 생각 없어
I don't plan to negotiate, either
나도 당신하고는 협상할 생각 없어
Pass the phone to Negro
흑귀나 바꿔 줘
Don't know why he calls you from my hood
왜 내 전화에 대고 자넬 바꾸라지?
What's up, Hau?
왜? 예 회장
I'm with Gandhi all the way
내가 할 말은 감지가 다 했다
He's not paying, neither will I!
감지가 안 내면 나도 안 내
Heard you and Gandhi have been tight
듣자니까 감지하고 왕래가 찾다면서?
The heroin you two smuggled got robbed
같이 에로인을 운반하다 잡혀서
Lost several millions each, right?
수백 만 달러씩 손애를 봤다지?
Luckily ! found the stuff in your warehouse
다행이도 당신 장고에서 찾았어
Want me to hand it back to Gandhi now?
그걸 감지한테 념길까?
What's he talking about?
이봐, 뭐래?
Among the Tsim Sha Tsui Big Fives...
침사추이의 5개 파 중에서
Wah and Negro paid up
국화와 흑귀가 냈고
Counting Sam, that's 3 to 2
침형까지 합치면 3대 2야
I'm the youngest here. Gotta pay!
내가 제일 어린데 안 낼 수 없잖아?
See ya!
그럼, 난 같게
Don't think too much. Cheers!
깊이 생각말고 마셔!
Pay my share for me!
예가에 줄 세금 좀 내 줘!
Mr. Ngai went to eat, Inspector Wong
반장님, 예 회장이 식사하러 나갔어요
A bit late for chowing, don't you think?
예 회장 식사가 늦으셨군요?
My dad always came here after work
아버진 일을 마치면 여기 와서 드셨죠
l have to keep up the ritual
저도 일이 끝나서 똑같이 하는 겁니다
Want to join us?
왜요? 함께 드시겠소?
It's your seat from now on. Must be tough
이제 당신 자리가 됐군 고생 많겠어
Not at all
벼 마쓰으 로 르미르--
You guys worked all night for nothing
이 밤에 힘들게 출동했는데
Now that's tough
소득이 없으니 그게 고생이죠
Well done, Hau
예 회장 오늘은 운이 아주 좋군
Hope you can keep it up
항상 그러길 바라지
Don't let it turn into a tragedy. Let's go
비극이 일어나는 건 보고 싶지 않다, 가지
What did you say?
뭐라 그랬어?
We want to celebrate
샴페인을 턴트릴 거라구!
Kwun's dead
예곤이 죽었으니까
Time to pop the champagne
죽하를 해야 할 것 아나?
Want me to pop one for you?
내가 하나 따 드릴까요?
What?
뭐야?
Want to mess with cops?
경찰을 지겠다고?
Officers!
경찰 나리들!
The Ngai's are in mourning
오늘 예가에서 한 사람을 잃었는데
What more do you want?
뭘 더 바라시죠?
Let's go
가세! 가자!
Sam
침형!
Dad used to operate street gambling here
아버진 이곳에 노름판을 열었는데
Started out as...
돈 몇 푼 가지고 사업을 시작애서
a dime-and-nickel business
지금에 이르렸어
Now who doesn't know his name?
침사추이에서는 알려진 인물이었지
He often said
항상 그러셨어 뿌린 만큼...
What goes around comes around
거둔다고 말이야
And now he's...
근데 그렇게 되실 줄은...
I'll always remember this day
오늘을 영원이 기억아겠어
It's all good, honey. Want some snacks?
모든 게 좋아 과자 좀 들겠어?
Good to hear that. Just come home
좋아요, 집으로 가요
An officer has to have a clean background
경찰이 되려면 뒤가 깨끗애야 한다
Though you cut your ties with the Ngai's...
모친의 성을 따고 왕래를 안 한다지만
..you still share the same father with Hau
너와 예 회장은 부친이 같다
That means you lied on your application
이는 배경을 어위 보고한 것이니
l have but to let you go
년 퇴교를 당하게 된다
But before you leave...
단, 가기 전에
..go see "Mr. Wrong Socks" first
양말을 잘못 신었던 그 친구를 보고 가라
Still want to be a cop?
아직도 경찰이 되고 싶나?
Can I still?
가능합니까?
Only if you can give me a good reason
그럴만한 이유를 대기만 하면!
l want to be a righteous person
좋은 사람이 되고 싶습니다
If you want to be a cop...
경찰이 되고 싶다면
..then lend me a hand. Simple as that
나를 돕는 길 외엔 다른 방법이 없다
You pick me 'cause I'm Hau's brother right?
예 회장의 동생이라 절 택하신 건가요?
When the time comes will you arrest him yourself?
기회가 된다면 직접 잡을 수 있겠나?
How do I start?
어떻게 시작애야 되죠?
Brace
꿈어 앉아!
You okay?
괜찮나?
Hanging in there?
견딜만 애?
Does it still hurt?
많이 아파?
My dad passed away today
아버지가 오늘 돌아가셨어
He was so good to me
날 젤 예뻐하셨는데
l asked the officer...
장례식에 다녀오게
..if ! could go to his funeral
잠깐만 내보내 달라고 했더니
The officer said...
뭐라고 그러는지 알아?
Know what it means to be a prisoner?
감목살이가 뭔지 아냐더라
It means you're not allowed
감옥살이는 설령 아버지가 돌아가셨어도
even to attend your father's funeral
가지 못하는 거래
Don't you know that?
알겠어!
Get out of here!
꺼져
Come on. Stop that
그만해
Are you nuts?
정신 나갔어?
You sent Yan to be a mole?
영인을 스파이로 보내겠다고?
Don't you know Hau's his half-brother?
예 회장이 친형이라는 거 몰라?
So what?
그게 어때서?
Bring me his file!
자료를 줘 봐!
So you're playing the boss now, huh?
내 상관 노릇을 하겠다는 거아?
You damn well know you the files are classified
기밀사안은 함부로 누설할 수 없어!
I treat you like a bro. Is this what I get?
형제저럼 대했는데 이렇게 나올 건가?
If you're a real bro, stop asking!
형제로 생각한다면 더 이상 묻지 마!
It's okay
그만해
Calm down!
진정아구
Speak slowly!
말로 하라고
She had an abortion!
애를 떼버렸다고
It's no big deal. Just a baby
그게 뭐 대단한 일이라고!
You can always have another one
떼면 또 낭고 다 그런 거지
I've been with you for four years
같이 산지가 4년이야
And I've bailed you out tons of times
경찰서에서 널 빼낸 게 수십 번이라구
One minute we're dining with my folks...
식구들과 식사아려 애도
..the next you'll be in a gang fight
둑하면 싸움질 애서 망쳐버리고
I don't want our baby to grow up like you
내 아기도 그렇게 되라고!
Do you understand?
니가 내 맘 알기나 애!
Why so uptight?
내가 그렇게 고지식애 보여?
No, nothing
아뇨
Uncle John says you're doing well
삼숙 말을 들으니 일을 잘한다더군
Ever thought about helping the family out?
여기서 일할 생각 없1?
[know you want to keep a distance from the Ngai's
우리 관계를 알리기 싫어한다는 거 알아
But we're blood brothers. It's a fact
우리가 친형제인 건 사실이야
It's my daughter's birthday this Sunday
일요일이 내 딸 생일인데
You're invited
널 초대아고 싶다
You really hate talking to me, huh?
정말 나랑 얘기하고 싶지 않니?
No
아뇨
Promoted already? Soon you'll be a superintendent
벌써 승진했어? 곧 경위가 된다며?
Might as well become a full time cop
이제 진짜 경찰이 된 거네?
Sam's kidding. Go ahead give me a smile
침형이 농담한 거야 그냥 웃어
Thanks for your intel these couple years
2년 동안 침형님 정보에 의지했어요
When you were still a rookie...
그 동안은 신참이라 피라미들 정보로
l helped you catch some small potatoes
쓰레기들을 청소 하도록 했지만
It's about time you caught some big shots
이제 진급도 했으니 거물들을 잡아아지
How about catching me?
날 잡아가는 건 어때?
Why so dirty? Or you can catch this hot chicks
성 추행범으로!
What're you doing?!
뭐 하는 거에요?
What a hot hootchie mama!
이렇게 아름다운 여자가 어디 있어?
Your man must be one good-looking bastard
애인이 멋있을 거야
It's you! Who else?
그야 당신이지
Gotta go
- 갈게 - 벌써요?
Gotta go meet Mr. Ngai
예 회장아고 약속이 있어
Sam's so good to you!
침형은 누님한테 잘애 주시네요
But he's not good to himself
자기 자신한테는 잘 못애
It's been four years
4년 됐어
He could be in charge now
보스가 될 수도 있었지만
But he gave everything to the Ngai's Already?
모든 걸 예가에 줘버렸지
Now the Ngai Family's all big and bad
지금은 아무도 예가에 대항 못애
Hau must've figured it out
그 후로... 영요도 범인을 찾고 있을 거야
For the past four years
4년 동안...
I haven't been sleeping well
아루도 편이 잔 적이 없어
I'm Inspector Wong Chi-Shing
난 황지성 국장이다
Don't worry, Mary
걱정 마세요, 누님!
l won't let anything happen to you
아무 일 없게 애드릴게요
Words, words, words
약속 지켜야 돼
I promise
물론이죠
Toss it up!
공 갖고 가서 놀아
Two days ago, a real estate agent came
며칠 전 한 부동산 업자가 집을 보러 왔었는데
Guess how much he offered?
그 사람이 얼마를 불렸는지 압니까?
One hundred sixty million!
일억 육천 일억 육천이라니...
What's wrong with Hong Kong? Tell me!
아이구 세상에나!
When my dad bought it
아버진 집을
it was 9 million...280 thousand
구백... 이십 팔만인가에 사셨는데
What a world!
때가 어느 땐데...
Moving, Mr. Ngai?
예 회장, 이사라도 가게?
1997 is approaching. Time to emigrate
97년에 이민이나 가려고요
No big deal
그게 뭐 어렵다고
We're just a phone call away
전화 한 통이면 맹이라고
I'm just worried about the phone bill
전화비가 들어 탈이죠
The phone company's greedy, you know
얼마나 폭리를 쥐하는지 알지 않습니까
I've discussed it with mom
어머니와 상의애 봤는데
Our businesses are on the right track
예가의 사업도 이제 궤도에 올라섰고
You guys helped out so much in the past
여러분도 오랫동안 도움을 주셨는데
don't want to be ungrateful
우리가 무책임하게 느껴지지 않도록
l want to split the business up...
여길 떠나게 되면 우리 사업을
among you guys
여러분과 나눌까 합니다
Treat it as a gift or a retirement fund
수고비 명목도 좋고 공동경비도 좋죠
Let's eat! Take whatever you want!
드세요 마음껏 가져다 드세요
We should hang out like this more often
앞으로도 자주 모여 얘기하도록 합시다
Mr. Ngai
회장님!
Are you leaving for real?
정말 가실 겁니까?
After you're gone, hell will break loose!
가시면 복잡해 집니다
You're a Buddhist, aren't you, Sam?
침, 부저님을 믿나?
Easy to start. Hard to let go
쉽게 얻은 것은 버리기 힘들어
I'm letting go. Be happy for me
내가 버리겠다면 기뻐애 줘아지
I've thought about it
내 생각엔...
Cocaine will be the future
앞으로 코카인 천지가 될 거야
Those four ship it in small bags from S. America
네 사람이 남미에서 소량을 들여오는데
Small-timers!
그 걸로는 안 돼
I've closed a deal with the Thais
내가 태국에다 얘기해 으니까
You'll have the monopoly
당신이 독자적으로 들여오면
You'll be the top dog. Leader of the pack
보스는 당신이 되고 모두 따를 거야
Go to Thailand and wrap up the logistics
태국에 가서 마무리 만 잘아고 오면 돼
You plan to get rid of those four?
네 사람을 없애버릴 건가요?
Move closer to the right, please
자, 오른쪽으로 붙으세요!
Yan
영인!
Come join the family portrait
와서 같이 찍자
Stand next to me!
여기 서!
l haven't been around much these two years
2년 동안 홍콩에 머문 시간이 적었어
It's rare to spend time...
그래서 오늘저럼
.. With the whole family like this
온 가족이 모두 모이기가 어려웠지
Your siblings are in legit businesses
누나와 형, 동생은 평범아게 사니까
It's time you helped out the family
네가 와서 좀 도와줘아겠다
Everything dad did was for the family
아버지가 한 일은 가족을 위애서였어
I did the same
나도 마찬가지고
Hope you will, too
너도 그러길 바래
A deal's coming up next week Come with me
다음주에 거래가 있는데 같이 가자
I'll call you
그 때 연락하마
I think he's taking the deal seriously
이번 거래는 중요아기 때문에 직접 갈 거야
He'll go in person next Wednesday
다음 주 수요일 14일이야
The 14th... Kwun's memorial
그 날이 곤의 기일이라고!
Hau wants to whack the Big Four
보스 4명을 죽일 거야
Why does he send Sam away?
근데 왜 한침은 제외시켰지?
Don't know. Sam should be of help to him!
모르겠어요 한침이 돔고 있나 봐요
Unless he wants to kill Sam also!
한침도 죽이려 아지 않을까?
I've been following you around for days!
며칠을 계속 따라다너
I'm your superior after all
어찌됐건 간에 난 자네 상사야
I want to know what your plan is
앞으로 어떻게 할 건지 알고 싶어
The Ngai's are your family
예씨 집안은 네 가족인데
Do you really know what you're doing?
무슨 짓을 하는지 알고 있는 거야?
Sirl
국장님!
I'm a cop!
전 경찰이에요
Good
좋아
Give me a salute
경례 좀 해봐
I've booked a table. Care for dinner?
식당을 예약애 났는데 시간 있나?
Do I look good in my cap?
내 모자 멋있지?
Looking good?
저 어때요?
What'll you do in Thailand in that outfit?
이렇게 입고 태국 가서 뭐아게?
Have some shark fin
아긴요
A massage. Get two whores for a threesome
그냥 먹고 마시고 놀아아죠
That's for sure
다 아시면서
Honey!
여보!
What?
왜?
Why didn't you tell me about your trip?
태국에 간단 말 왜 안 했어요?
It's a business trip! Not for fun!
일 때문에 가는 거야
Don't worry. I'll behave
걱정 마! 딴 짓 안 할게
Hau plans to whack Wah and those guys
예 회장이 소두목들을 죽일 거래요
l know
나도 알아
But do you know you're his target too?
당신도 그 중 하나란 거 몰라요?
Nonsense! How can that be?
함부로 말하지 마 그럴 리 없어
Just wait for me at the airport!
어쩌나 공항에서 기다려요
Time to board, Sam!
침형, 타시죠
That's all 1 can do for now
지금 할 수 있는 건 그게 전부야
Call Sam again when the plane lands
침이 도착하면 다시 전화애 봐
I'm going to kill Hau tonight
오늘 밤 예 회장을 숙여버릴게요
Don't do anything rash!
성급하게 굴지 마
I'm not being rash!
성급한 게 아니에요
Four years ago...
4년 전 기억 때문에 그래요
.. you told me to kill Kwun
곤을 없애라고 할 때 말이에요
So what? Want to blackmail me now?
그게 뭐? 지금 협박아는 건가?
I'm not blackmailing you
협박0 아니에요
We simply passed the point of no return!
이젠 돌이킬 수 없는 일이에요
I'll send everybody away
때가 되면 모두 보내버릴 거야
Tonight's operation's top secret
오늘 밤 작전은 절대 비밀이다
We're divided into three teams
모두 3개조로 나뉘다
Team A watches here
쓰조는 이쪽 출구를 막고
Team B here
ㅁ조는 이쪽이다
Wait for my order before doing anything
내 명령이 없이는 움직이지 마라
Team C follows the target until...
(조는 용의자를 주시하는데 . . .
Nobody told me about the date change!
날짜가 바뀌었는데 왜 통보를 안 했지?
You know Hau changes his mind all the time
알다시피 예 회장은 다루기 힘든 놈이야
You think Yan's the only mole?
자네만 스파이를 보낸 줄 아나?
My man's been undercover for seven years!
내가 보낸 스파이도 7년을 쫓아다너
Where's the deck of cards?
카드 있나?
We'll run the show together tonight
그럼 오늘 작전은 같이 결정하세
Let's go!
출동!
Sir
국장님!
How are you?
안녕하시오
Don't move...
꼼짝마!
Hau
예 회장!
Zipping it till your lawyer gets here?
변호사가 와야 입을 열 건가?
Come on, cooperate with us!
협조 좀 해
In fact, l appreciate your cooperation
오이려 여러분이 협조애 줘서 고많소
Are you speaking Zen, Mr. Ngai?
예 회장 너무 심오한 말이라
I don't get it
이해할 수가 없군
Dad used to say...
아버님이 그러셨소
.. the way things work in the streets...
자신이 무슨 일을 하던 간에
... what goes around always comes around
뿌린 만큼 거둔다고
He died four years ago. It's about time
돌아가신 지 4년 됐는데 지금 이맘때 즈음이겠군
The stove's hot enough now
사장님, 숫불 다 피웠습니다
She's here, boss
사장님, 왔습니다
You're here now
당신 부하들이 모두 여기 있는데
What can you swing?
뭘 할 수 있다는 거지?
Wait and see
그건 모르지
Got it! Sir
반장님, 알아냈습니다
The two foreigners are private eyes
그 서양인들은 사립탐정입니다
Thailand, of course
나야 태국이지
Come back right away!
빨리 돌아와요
Are you nuts? Why should I come back?
미졌어? 내가 왜 돌아가?
Don't ask questions! Just come back!
아무 말 말고 빨리 돌아와요
Hau wants you dead!
예 회장이 당신을 죽이려고 애요
Nonsense! I'm working for him as we speak!
엇소리, 난 예 회장 일을 돔는 거야
Listen to me!
내 말 들어요
I killed Kwunt
고으 늬느= 내가 죽였어요
You've got a VCR?
비디오 플레이어 있소?
Isn't it good?
재미있는 건가?
What an awesome show!
아주 재미있지
Take care. Run if you have to
조심애 일이 생기면 튀어
What did Hau say?
예 회장이 뭐라는데?
Sam. Sunny!
- 침! - 써니!
Mr. Ngai told me to take good care of you!
예 회장님께서 잘 모시라고 했습니다
Four years ago...
4년 전 기억 때문에 그래요
.. you told me to kill Kwun
고으 ㄴㄴ 없애라고 할 때 말이에요
So what? Want to blackmail me now?
그게 뭐? 지금 협박아는 건가?
I'm not blackmailing you
협박0 아니에요
We simply passed the point of no return!
이젠 돌이킬 수 없는 일이에요
I'll send everybody away
때가 되면 모두 보내버릴 거야
l hired Alan and Johnson...
알란과 존슨은
..to investigate my father's murder
아버지의 살인자를 찾기 위애 내가 의뢰한 사람들이요
Who would've known? The police conspired...
당신네 경찰들이 아버지를 죽인 줄은 정말 몰랐소
to murder my father
아버지같이
A law-abiding citizen
선량한 시민을 살애하다니
SP Luk
육 국장!
Isn't that an officer in the video?
화면에 있는 사람이 경찰 아니요?
Whether to nail him or not...
어떻게 할거요? 잡을지 안 잡을지
. that's up to you
알아서들 하시오
What a good show!
보기 좋구만!
You're so friggin’ photogenic
화면발이 좋은데?
Four years ago...
4년 전에...
How much did Sam's woman pay you?
한침의 여자한테 얼마 받았어?
Give me another chance, Mr. Ngai
회장님 한 번만 봐 주세요
I gave them a chance four years ago
4년 전에 이미 기회를 줬는데
They didn't take it
받아들이지 않았다
If l give you a chance
지금 너한테 기회를 준다면
Are you going to take it today?
받아들이겠나?
You've been with us for seven years now
년 예가와 7년을 함께 해왔지만
You're a cop
년 경찰이고
We're the bad guys
우리는 조직이다
Time to accept our fates
모든 게 숙명이야
You can't blame me
날 탓하지 마라
Your Inspector Wong killed my dad
황 국장이 아버지를 죽였기 때문이야
Any words from Sam?
침형한테 연락 없었어?
Sam called me
연락이 왔었는데
He said he was fine
아무 일 없대요
He asked you to wait for him here
여기 숨어있으면 곧 온대요
Where're your folks?
가족들은 어디 있지?
All emigrated
이민 갔어요
You didn't go with them?
년 안 가고?
Let's go, Sam! We got rid of the Thais
침형, 빨리 가요 아무도 안 쫓아와요
Let's go!
빨리 가요
You know you're not going to make it
도망가지 못한다는 거 알지?
l know
안다
My girl's in danger in Hong Kong
내 여자가 옹콩에서 위험에 저애 있다
Please help me
한 번만 도와줘
Why should I?
내가 왜 도와줘야 하는데?
‘Cause I'll help you whack your boss
내가 너희 보스를 죽여줬잖아
I Know you want to be in charge
그 자리를 원한 거 알아
Moreover
더구나. . .
I've been treating you as a pal
난 너를 친구로 생각해 왔다
Don't believe him, Sam! Don't!
믿지 마요! 침형 믿지 말아요
Get lost!
저리 비켜
Don't believe him! Get lost!
- 믿지 마요! - 비켜!
Sorry, Sam
미안하네, 침형
Are you here to arrest me?
잡으러 왔나?
If you're going to kill Hau
예 회장을 죽이려 한다면...
I will
잡을 거야
Then there's nothing to talk about
그럼 할 말 없지
l spoke with my superiors
상부에는 보고했네
They're with you all the way this time
이번만은 자네를 지지할 거야
How?
어떻게?
[ conspired in murder!
살인을 교사했는데?
Even the Brits agree that...
상부에서도 모두 동의했네
..we can't let the triads break us
조직에서 날뛰는 건 용서할 수 없다고!
The whole department's behind you
지금 경찰은 모두 자네 편이야
Good enough?
그럼 충분한가?
Where's your deck of cards?
카드 있지?
The higher points win
높은 사람이 이기는 거야!
Come back with me to the department
서에 가서 회의나 하세
The key!
열쇠!
Forget it. l screwed up
안 그래도 복잡해
No need to drag everyone down with me
피곤하게 하지 마
We found this deck in our first outing together
우리가 처음 공동 조사를 할 때부터
You've been keeping it all this time
가지고 다녕지
I knew that all along
난 알고 있었어
It's your turn to listen for once
이번엔 내 말 들어!
We're like brothers
형제나 마찬가진데
Think I'm just gonna be a spectator?
자네 일을 어떻게 두고만 보겠나?
Law's my snitch in the Ngai Family
로는 내가 보낸 스파이였네
He hasn't contacted me for days
며칠째 아무 연락 없어
Neither has Yan!
영인도 그렇고!
The key!
열쇠!
Help!
도와줘요!
Help! Get some help!
도와줘요! 제발. . .
Why did you lie to me?
왜 거짓말했어?
I didn't!
아니에요
Something happened to Sam!
침한테 일이 생겼어
I told you I was a simple woman
내가 말했잖아 난 단순한 여자라고
l have to do something for my husband
남편을 위해선 무슨 일이든 애야 돼
I'm going to Thailand
태국으로 가야겠어
Please don't go!
가지 말아요
Forget it! You don't have to follow us anymore
됐어, 이제 날 따라다닐 필요 없어
[ mean, I don't want you to go
말했잖아요 가지 말라구요
You've been with Sam for years
솔직이 침형하고는 오래 됐잖아요
Has it occurred to you...
생각 안 해봤어요?
Maybe Sam's dead!
침형은 죽었어요
What did you say?
무슨 말이야?
l can take care of you
제가 돌봐드릴게요
What're you doing?
무슨 짓이아?
I don't want you to go!
보내기 싫어요
You're out of line!
이거 못 뇌?
Listen up!
잘 들어
I'm your boss's woman!
난 네 보스의 여자야
Don't let me see your face again!
다신 나 볼 생각 하지마!
She will go to the airport tonight...
오늘 밤 공항으로 갈 겁니다
Hello? Hello?
여보세요, 여보세요?
I killed Kwunt
곤은 내가 죽였어
Aman treats me well
사랑에 빠지면
I'd do anything
뭐든지 할 수 있어
About Inspector Wong conspiring in murder
황지성 국장의 살인 교사 사건에 관해
This is the 11th internal hearing
경감 세 분을 모셔 심문하겠습니다
Inspector Wong
황지성 국장
do you have any question?
질문 있습니까?
No...
없습니다
No
없습니다. . .
An inspector should possess leadership skills
국장이면 리더십을 갖춰야만 한다
Mr. Lau
유경관
you joined as a police constable
자년 일반 경관의 신분으로서
Could you tell the promotion board
반장 승진을 요구하는 이유를
why you deserve to be promoted?
설명애 보도록 애라
Of course
그러죠
On April 11, 1995...
1995년 04월 11일
The department received this tape
감찰과에서 이 테이프를 받았소
Accusing you of conspiring in a murder
조직과 공모애서 살인교사를 한 게 사실이요?
l confess, sir
죄를 인정합니다
It's already 1997
올애는 1997년이다
Before the 1st of July
7월 1일 전까지
If we don't receive your PO assessment report
자네의 승진보고를 통과시키지 않아도
Do you still think you can be promoted?
다시 기회가 있을 거라 생각하나?
In Chinese, there is a saying
이런 말이 있습니다
With a new king come new followers
"황제가 바뀌면 신하도 바뀌다"
So, I guess we will have to start all over again
때문에 우리는 다시 시작애야 합니다
What happened to you?
왜 그렇게 변한 건가?
If I told you...
만약 우리 경찰에서
..that the evidence couldn't stand
증거 불충분으로 사건을 말소시키면
would you like to start over?
다시 시작할 마음이 있나?
I'm sorry. I broke the law
죄송합니다 전 죄를 지었습니다
What do you think of the police force's morale after 1997?
97년 이후 경찰을 바라보는 시각은?
Chinese people are sentimental
중국인은 감정에 민감합니다
I hope the law will continue to back me up
법은 우리와 함께 할 거라 믿습니다
But, I strongly believe in myself, sir!
전 자신감이 있고 자신을 믿습니다
I'm grateful to all of you
절 믿어주셔서 감사하지만
But I've got no confidence left. I lost!
자신이 없습니다 전 졌습니다
What about Luk then?
육 국장은 어쩌고?
Can you face him if you give up now?
자네가 이러는 게 미안하지도 않나?
The war's not over
싸움은 아직 끝나지 않았어
We all want a closure to this incident
우리 모두 사건을 잘 종결애서
Hong Kong is not run by the Ngai Family
몽콩은 예가의 구역이 아니란 걸 널리 알리고 싶네
Here's a file from the Interpol
이건 인터폴 자료야
Read it before your make up your mind
보고 나서 결정하지
Ever been to a funeral in Thailand?
태국식 장레에 참석해 봤나?
A few months ago...
몇 달 전에. . .
[had one for my wife
아내를 위해 장례식을 치러줬지
The monks chanted for three full days
스님도 불러서 삼 일 동안 경도 읽게 아고...
I didn't shed a single tear
삼 일 동안 눈물 한 방울 안 나오더군
On the day of the burial...
마지막 날
.. they left the casket in the living room
일꾼들이 관을 거실로 가져오는 거야
l was mad
미치겠더군
l wanted to beat them up
그 놈들을 죽도로 패주고 싶었어
The monk told me
그때 스님이 그러더군
it's a tradition in Thailand
태국의 풍습이라고
The deceased...
죽은 사람과
As long as we keep her company...
얼마 동안
for a little while longer
시간을 보내줘야
she can attain eternal peace
망자가 편히 쉽 수 있다고 말이야
But I asked the monk
하지만 난 스님에게 물었지
what if my wife was not in the coffin?
아내는 지금 관 속에 없는데
Could she still attain eternal peace?
편안이 철 수 있겠나고!
Sorry about your wife
자네 부인 일은 미안하게 됐네
The monk placed his hand here
스님이 내 여길 누르면서
He said, "No problem
「괜찮습니다
Your wife's here."
당신 부인은 여기 있지 않습니까'라고 하더군
And here's exactly...
마침 여긴
..where the Thais shot me!
종에 맞은 자리였어
So I told myself
난 스스로에게 중고했지
I've passed the point of no return
다신 돌이킬 수 없다고!
Testifying against Hau could be dangerous
이번에 몽콩에서 증언하는 건 위험해
I believe in you. You're so handsome
난 자네처럼 잘생긴 사람은 언제나 믿지
Haven't heard that for ages. Thanks
오랜만에 듣는 소리군 고마워
What's your plan?
무슨 계획이라도 있나?
Just trying to do my best
최선을 다애아지
No big deal. It's my job
어차피 내 일인데
I'll leave Hong Kong when it's all over
이번 일만 마치면 몽콩을 떠날 거야
You've changed
자네 좀 변했군
Baby
아가야
You diluted the coke, didn't you?
이거 가짜지?
Got anything to say?
할 말 있어?
Take it all then!
너나 실컷 먹어
Don't go too far, Yan
영인, 심하게 다루지 마
It'd break the boys' morale
너무 그러면 일할 맛 나겠어?
Mr. Ngai asked me to be in charge here
회장님이 시킨 일입니다
Don't like it? Drive him to the hospital!
맘에 안 들면 병원에 데려 가세요
No matter what
그 친구들이 잘못했다고 애도
they're elders after all
선배들이잖아?
You've got lots to learn from them
앞으로 배워야 될 것들이 많아
Uncle John will retire in a few years
삼숙은 몇 년 후면 은퇴할 거야
You know what I mean?
무슨 말인지 알아?
I don't need any hiccups now
문제가 생기는 걸 원치 않는다
The Labor Athletic Association has a formal...
오늘밤 노동제육회 연회가 있어
.. for us Political Consultative candidates
정치협의회 우보는 모두 참석할 거야
If everything works out
이번 일만 잘 되면
our family will no longer live in shadows
우리 예가는 앞으로 인간답게 살 수 있다
Mr. Cheung
장 회장님!
Mr. Ngai
예 회장!
How are you? Good. Good
- 안녕하십니까? - 안녕하셨소?
When Solicitor Hung mentioned you
옹 변호사가 당신 얘기를 하는데
I didn't believe him
믿을 수가 있어아죠
You're amazingly young, Mr. Ngai
예 회장, 보아하니 정말 젊으셨군요
What's your Zodiac?
무슨 띠죠?
Ox
소멈니다
The Year of the Ox
소띠
Ox's good
소띠 좋지
Director Chan likes young people
진 주임은 젊은 사람을 좋아아니까
I'll introduce you later. Thanks
- 소개시켜 드리겠소 - 고많습니다
Really?
그래요?
Director Chan said he hated the triads
진주임 말로는 소폭을 꺼린다던데?
That's right, SP Leung
야 겨가니 ㅎㅁㅁㅁ
Mr. Ngai's been invited to consult the police
회장님은 경찰 소송 전문가로 소대됐죠
Really? Congratulations!
그래요? 축하합니다
Where do you golf these days, Chan?
진 선생, 요즘엔 어디서 골프 치나?
What's your handicap these days?
중산에서 지죠
How are you? My name's Ngai...
- 안녕하세요? - 예영요라고 합니다
Mr. Ngai Wing-Hau
예영효 회장!
I'm Mr. Ngai's solicitor
전 예 회장님의 변호사입니다
Tonight's a celebration for HK's hand-over
오늘은 노동제육회 연회가 있는 날이니
All other businesses can wait
연회가 끝나고 말씀하시죠
What if l say no?
안 된다면?
Got any problem with that?
어떡하시겠소?
Mr. Ngai
예 회장!
You're a suspect
당신은
in several murder cases in 1995
95년 발생한 살인사건 용의자로 지목됐소
You're under arrest
구속영장이요
This is your arrest warrant
당신을 제포아겠소
Everything you say
지금부터 하는 말은
will be recorded...
기록으로 남아
and could be used as evidence against you
증거 자료로 사용됩니다
Do you have any question?
이의 있습니까?
No
없습니다
I looked through their files
자료를 살펴봤는데
The murder charges won't stand
살애 혐의는 요건 성립이 안 되지만
But your being a triad boss...
삼합회의 보스 신분이기 때문에
That one will stick
죄를 면할 수는 없습니다
The unions and the political parties called
형, 각 정당에서 전화가 왔는데
They want to withdraw their invitations
연회 초청장을 돌려달랍니다
Words from the HK and Macau Affairs Office
변호사 협회에서도
They have revoked your candidacy
후보자격이 박탈 됐다고 연락 왔다
Call Beijing. Get some friends to help
북경에 전화애서 도움을 청애봐요
Let me try
내가 애볼게
Forget it
그만 두세요
They even found a dead man to testify against you
그쪽에선 죽은 사람도 찾아냈어요
Everyone knows how loyal Sam was to you
한침이 예가에 충성한 건 아실 겁니다
Now he's the prosecution's witness It's over
그가 증인으로 나서면 끝장입니다
Sorry. Can't help you
죄송합니다 도울 수가 없군요
You said there'd be no problem!
아무 문제 없다며?
Everyone's watching how we will react
이미지가 좋다면서
What're you going to do?
이제 와서 뭘니까?
What can I do?
그럼 중국정부에
Threaten the government?
협박이라도 할까요?
Don't take it the wrong way
그런 뜻이 아니요
We're all in the same boat
어차피 같은 배를 탄 거 아니요
Time for me to get off then
전 관두겠습니다
I'm just a lawyer. Not one of you
전 변오사지 당신들 동료가 아닙니다
I don't intend to sink with you. Sorry
같이 침몰하긴 싫습니다
Yes
네!
Sam has a wife and a daughter are in Thailand!
한침의 둘째 부인이 태국에 있습니다
It's your call
알아서 해
Sis
누나!
You and the brothers should take mom...
형하고 영의와 같이 어머니를 모시고
... and go to Hawaii for a while
하와이에 잠시 가 계세요
Okay. Haven't been there for a while
그래 좋아 거기 가 본 지도 오래 됐어
Are you going to be all right?
너 온자 괜찮겠니?
I'll be fine
괜찮아요
Sorry I can't help the family
미안해요
The key thing now is you turn out okay
가족들을 돌보지 못애서
Take care of mom!
어머니를 부탁애요
Don't worry. Leave it to us three
걱정 마라 우린 셋인데 뭐
Even with my testimony
내가 증인으로 출석한다고 애도
Hau will only get a couple years
예 회장은 몇 년 살다 나올 거야
It's true
그건 그래
He'll have to whack you to get life
자네를 죽인다면 종신형을 살겠지
l have to thank you
정말 고많네
Without you
자네가 없었다면
l could never have come back
몽콩으로 돌아오지 못했을 거야
Save it! I'm busy these days
그런 말은 그만 뒤 요즘 바빠
Anything you need, ask them
필요한 게 있으면 저 친구들한테 말해
They'll protect you
우리 요원들이 보오애 줄 거야
Sam!
침형!
Thanks
고마워
Good. Been transferred to the CIB
그런대로요 정보과로 옮겼어요
Will be Inspector-in-Training next month
다음달에 반장교육을 받아요
Did Mary call you...
메리가 떠날 때
.. before she left...?
자네를 안 찾았나?
Don't be too hard on yourself, Sam
침형, 이제 잊으세요
Inspector Wong said to find you if 1 needed anything
필요한 게 있으면 널 찾으라고 하던데
Will you really help me?
날 도울 수 있어?
I thought you wouldn't come
안 올 줄 알았어
Why's that?
제가 왜요?
So here we are
왜 그랬죠?
It's been two years
2년 됐어요
Because of my father's case
아버지 살인사건과 관련됐다고
you didn't dare to call me for two years?
2년을 안 찾아요?
You couldn't face me?
볼 낮이 없어서?
Right
그래
All you need to nail Hau is in the safe
금고 안에 예가의 범죄 증거가 있어요
I've organized the files according to dates
사건 내용과 일시도 정리애 고!
Why do you still help me?
왜 아직까지 돕는 거지?
I'm not helping you
당신을 돔는 게 아니에요
I'm a cop
난 경찰이에요
l want to keep my promises to SP Luk!
육 국장님과 했던 약속을 지키는 거죠
And I don't want to be a mole any more
이제 첩자가 싫어요
Two more years and I'll become the top dog
2년만 더 있으면 보스가 돼요
What for? To end up in prison?
왜요? 감옥 가고 싶어요?
Let's bury the past
과거는 잊었어요
Just bring me back into the department
빨리 사건을 마무리애서 복귀시커 줘요
Give me a desk
아주 편한 자리로!
Make sure it has a sea view
바다가 보여야 돼요
And don't let me see your face again
그리고 국장님은 안 보게 애줘요
Don't worry
걱정 마
You won't see me any more
볼 수 없을 거야
One more thing
또 한 가지!
[ couldn't spell some of the words
서류 안에 못 쓴 글자가 있어요
Come find me if you don't understand
못 알아보면 불러요
But don't mess up the order
오래 작업한 거니까 저리 잘애요
I'll kill you if you mess that up!
엉망으로 저리아면 숙여버릴 거에요
That's great. Put me out of misery!
그거 괜찮지 빚은 갖을 테니까
Thank you, officer
고마, 진경관!
The trial will start in three days
침, 증거를 잡았네 사흘 뒤에 재판이야
OCTB!
강력반입니다
Inspector Wong! Sam's gone!
황 국장님 한침이 사라졌답니다
He escaped through the kitchen
부억을 통해 달아났을 겁니다
Who was guarding the kitchen?
부억은 누가 지켰지?
Sorry, sir
죄송합니다, 국장님
Sam'd made a call to Thailand...
한침이 떠나기 전
.. before he escaped
태국으로 전화를 했습니다
Mr. Ngai
회장님!
What do you want from me?
무슨 일로 찾으셨죠?
You called me
당신이 전화했지 않소?
So tell me how you can help me
어떻게 도울 건지 말애줄 줄 알았는데
Am I right? Sit down
아닌가? 앉아!
Whack me!
죽여주쇼
Kill me and it's all over!
날 죽이면 천하가 태평할 거요
Why should I?
내가 왜 죽여?
Haven't done that kind of stuff for ages
그런 짓은 안 한지 오래 됐어
Everything can be negotiated
침, 말로 하자고!
Hong Kong's big enough for us both, Sam
몽콩은 넓어
Let's forget about the past
과거는 덮어두고!
You will kill me
어차피 죽일 거면
You'll kill me tonight
지금 당장 죽어요
But who's gonna take care of your family?
당신을 죽이면 저자식은 어쩌고?
Just in!
예 회장이 태국에 있는
Hau has Sam's wife and daughter as hostages
침의 부인과 딸을 잡아두고 있답니다
That's his Thai maid!
그들은 한침이 고용한 가짜아
l managed to stay alive all these years
몇 년 동안... 죽지 않았던 건
It's all because...
바로. . .
... [have some good buddies in Thailand
좋은 태국 친구가 있었기 때문이요
You want to take this call
전화 좀 받아봐요
It's from Hawaii
하와이에요
Your whole family's there
가족들이 모두 거기 있더군
Hello! Mr Ngai
예 회장, 안녕하시오
My boss asked me
우리 보스가
to take good care of your family
당신 가족 좀 돌보라는데
Daddy! Where are you?
아빠, 어디 있어?
Mr. Ngai!
회장님!
Shut up!
닥쳐!
You'll whack me tonight. I told you so
오늘 날 죽이라고 했잖소?
Put it down, Ngai Wing-Hau!
예영요, 총을 내려나라
Let him
나 뒤!
He tried to kill me once before
과거에도 한 번 죽였으니까
Let him do it again!
또한번 죽이라고 해요!
Officers
경찰 여러분!
After he shoots me...
놈이 날 죽이면
..it'll be your call to shoot him or not
맘대로 쏘시오
What goes around comes around!
뿌린 만큼 거두게 될 것이다
Two questions
두 가지만 묻겠네
Did you kill his whole family?
가족들을 모두 죽여버렸나?
Of course not!
물론 아니지
My buddies and I were just scaring him!
태국 친구를 시커서 겁준 것뿐이야
Would you believe me if 1 said no?
아니라고 하면 믿겠어?
l expected to die here
난 여기서 죽을 각오를 했어!
It was my only way
그 방법밖에 없었어
Sorry
미안하네
Did you know how hard I worked...
내가 얼마나 많은 시간을 들여
.. to collect tons of evidence...
증거를 수집했는지 알아?
..to put him away for life?
충분이 종신형을 고할 수 있었어
The Thai guy, Sam
침형, 태국 친구요
Thank you
고많네
It's all good
다 잘 됐어
We're now partners
이제 우린 파트너야
Cocaine straight to HK from now on
이제부터 옹콩에서 마약을 팔자고!
Should ! wrap up the Ngai episode?
예가 사람들은 다 처지할까?
Paul...
폴!
Maybe we shouldn't go too far
그럴 필요까지는 없잖아?
It was pure luck that you bumped into me
그때 날 만나서
Otherwise you would've been killed
목숨을 건지게 된 거야
We were destined to be partners...
내가 자네를 죽이지 않았기에
.. when my gun failed to kill you
우린 파트너가 된 거라고!
You can never go too far. Get it?
그런데도 처치할 필요가 없어?
The hand-over ceremony of Hong Kong...
옹콩의 중국 반환을 위한 옹콩 반환식이
... commenced earlier at 11:20
11시 20분 옹콩 컨벤션센터에서 시작됐습니다
A British flag
동시에 영국 국기가
rose up in the hall
식장 안에 휘날립니다
The ceremony was dignified
기념식은 아주 장엄하지만
Yet it'd had its share of relaxed moments...
행사 전 분위기는
before its commencement
활기로 넘졌습니다
When both countries’ marching bands played
양측 군악대가 연주하는 동안
some Chinese representatives took pictures
중국대표단은 기념촬영을 아고
Prince Charles
찰스 왕세자와
and Governor Patten were smiling
패튼 종독이 지켜봅니다
As the ceremony officially commenced
기념식이 정식으로 시작됐습니다
Three British soldiers
영국군 세 명과
.. marched slowly onto the podium
천천이 국기 게양대를 향아고 있습니다
The Chinese soldiers...
세 명의 중국 인민애방군이
displayed the PRC flag
중국측에 자국기를 펼칩니다
Following their lead...
뒤이어
Three HK Royal Police officers...
세 명의 왕립 몽콩경찰
..emerged with
그리고 몽콩 특구기를 손에 든 세 명의 옹콩특구경찰이
three HK SAR Police officers
단상으로 향하고 있습니다
The three SAR officers displayed...
중국측에
... the HKSAR flag to the honorable guests
옹콩 특구기를 펼져 보입니다
And now
그와 동시에
all the guests have risen
기념식에 참석한 귀빈들이 모두 자리에서 일어납니다
It was exactly midnight
정확이 1997년
The arrival of July 1st, 1997
7월 1일 0시부로
with the HKSAR flag
옹콩 특구기가 함께 휘날리게 됐습니다
It also signified the beginning...
역사적인
...of the One Country Two Systems policy
일국양제 제도가 시작됨을 의미합니다
... of the People's Republic of China has been established
홍콩특별행정구가 정식으로 설립됐습니다
Okay. It's a deal
이제 됐어
You know what kind of boss is the worst?
어떤 보스가 제일 밥맛인지 알아?
Look's everything! Look how I shine!
외모가 중요애 내 얼굴을 봐!
What's your name, miss?
아가씨 이름이 뭐죠?
MAA...
버-^. .
M-A-Y...
버-&-.
M-A-R-Y
버-&--
Continuous Hell embodies 3 components:
우는 4 24442 7 시무, 공문, 주교무2